Now we are facing little children.
Teď jsou před námi malé děti.
They are the ones who are incarnations.
Ony jsou inkarnacemi.
They are the ones who are going to lead humanity
To ony povedou lidstvo
into some great advancement –
k nějakému velkému pokroku;
the humanity has to be looked after.
o lidstvo musí být postaráno.
They are tomorrow’s humanity. And we are today’s.
Ony jsou zítřejší lidstvo. A my jsme dnešní.
And what are we giving to them for them to follow?
A jaký jim dáváme vzor k následování?
What is their aim in life?
Jaký je cíl jejich života?
Very, very difficult to say.
To je velmi, velmi obtížné říci.
But with the Sahaja Yoga they will all go in the proper way,
Ale se Sahadža jógou půjdou všechny správným směrem,
they’ll behave in a proper way
budou se chovat správně
and the whole thing will be a different mass of Sahaja Yogis coming up.
a oni všichni vytvoří jinou spoustu sahadžajogínů budoucnosti.
But it is the duty of bigger Sahaja Yogis to look after them;
Je však povinností starších sahadžajogínů starat se o ně,
to have better moral standards, to have better lives
aby měly lepší morální standard, lepší život,
so that they follow your life and become genuinely good Sahaja Yogis.
aby šly ve vašich šlépějích a staly se opravdu dobrými sahadžajogíny.
It’s a very big responsibility, perhaps we don’t recognise it, we don’t understand,
Je to velká zodpovědnost, možná jsme to nepoznali, nepochopili,
but all these are little creatures which are after the image
ale oni všichni jsou malá stvoření, která budou k obrazu
of great souls and they should be brought up in that way,
velkých duší a takto by měly být vychovány,
respected in that manner and loved with great care.
respektovány a milovány s velkou péčí.
This is to be understood. The problem with our elderly people is this,
To je třeba pochopit. Problém s našimi dospělými je v tom,
that we do not consider them to be considered,
že my nepovažujeme za nutné brát je v úvahu,
to be bothered about, to be understood about. We think we are too intelligent,
zajímat se o ně, chápat je. Myslíme si, že jsme tak inteligentní,
too good and we need not waste our energy with them.
tak úžasní, že na ně nemusíme plýtvat svou energií.
This is the trouble of the elderly people.
To je problém dospělých.
But today when we are sitting here to worship Shri Ganesha,
Ale dnes, kdy tu sedíme, abychom uctili Šrí Ganéšu,
we should know they are all incarnations of Shri Ganesha
bychom si měli uvědomit, že jsou to všechno inkarnace Šrí Ganéši.
and they should be given proper attention, proper understanding about themselves.
A měly by dostat patřičnou pozornost, řádné porozumění sobě samým.
I find certain amount of children who are very well-behaved, which are very sensible,
Vidím určité množství velmi dobře vychovaných, velmi rozumných dětí.
and there are some who have no idea as to what they are doing.
A rovněž existují takové, které nemají ani ponětí, co dělají.
So it is the duty of the elders to put ideas into their head,
Takže je povinnost dospělých, aby jim předali představu
to proper understanding about themselves and the self-respect.
náležitého porozumění sobě samým a sebeúcty.
Same thing I would say for the elder Sahaja Yogis
Totéž bych řekla starším sahadžajogínům,
who have to look after their younger brothers and sisters.
kteří se starají o své mladší bratry a sestry.
In this family of ours which we call as Sahaja Yogis,
V této naší rodině, kterou nazýváme sahadžajogíny,
there are all kinds of people, all types, all behaviours.
jsou lidé nejrůznějšího druhu a typu, nejrůznějšího chování.
Of course, they should not be regimented, there should not be uniformity,
Samozřejmě, neměli by být řízeni, neměla by tu být uniformita,
but in that variety there should be with beauty,
ale v té rozdílnosti by měla být krása,
there should be beautiful trend of being one with each other.
měl by to být nádherný směr bytí jednoho s druhým.
For that, what should we do, is the problem.
Co bychom pro to mohli udělat, to je ta otázka.
What should the elders do to achieve that?
Co by měli starší udělat, aby toho dosáhli?
What is our solid contribution to their lives?
Jaký přínos trvalé hodnoty jim vnášíme do života?
The first will be to tell them who is Shri Ganesha,
Nejprve by se jim mělo říci, kdo je Šrí Ganéša
and that what are the qualities of Ganesha, what does He represent.
a jaké jsou kvality Šrí Ganéši, co představuje.
What does He represent, what qualities He has.
Co reprezentuje, jaké má kvality.
And once they start understanding, that though being a little boy,
A jakmile začnou chápat, že i když On je jen malý chlapec,
He’s so generous, He’s so kind, He’s so forgiving,
je tak štědrý, je tak laskavý, je tak odpouštějící.
they’ll be amazed because they are also small
Užasnou, protože oni jsou také malí,
and they’ll also take to that kind of life.
a začnou také vést takový život.
I find some children very sensible, very good here.
Vidím, že některé děti zde jsou velmi rozumné a velmi hodné.
Some are naughty and some don’t understand what we are doing here.
Některé jsou zlobivé a některé nechápou, co tady děláme.
Whatever it is, they are after all children.
Ať je to jakkoli, jsou to přece jen děti.
And what you have to do is to look after them, respect them,
A vy se o ně musíte starat, vážit si jich
and give them the full idea about Shri Ganesha.
a dát jim co nejúplnější představu o Šrí Ganéšovi.
I think everybody must have a statue of Shri Ganesha in your house,
Řekla bych, že každý by měl mít doma sošku Šrí Ganéši,
so the children will see it and ask, “Who is He? What is He doing here?”
aby ji děti uviděly a ptaly se: „Kdo to je? Co tady dělá?“
And you’ll be amazed how they will understand Him,
A užasnete, jak Mu porozumí,
how they will understand His qualities and how they will work it out.
jak porozumí Jeho kvalitám a jak to vypracují.
It is important for all of you to have at least one Shri Ganesha in your house,
Pro vás všechny je důležité mít doma alespoň jednoho Šrí Ganéšu,
so that you can tell your children that, ‘You all have to become like Him’.
abyste svým dětem mohli říct: „Vy všechny musíte být jako On.“
Now what are the qualities of Shri Ganesha?
Jaké jsou tedy kvality Šrí Ganéši?
They won’t understand chastity, they are too small,
Ony neporozumí cudnosti, jsou příliš malé,
they won’t understand all those qualities.
nebudou rozumět všem těmto kvalitám.
But one quality they will understand is to be honest. Is to be honest.
Ale jednou kvalitou, kterou pochopí, je být čestný. Být čestný.
Gradually you’ll find all difficult ones will go down, it will work out that way.
Uvidíte, postupně se všechny obtížné děti napraví, vypracuje se to.
Because you see, they don’t understand My lecture,
Protože, víte, ony nerozumí mým přednáškám,
they don’t understand what I am saying.
ony nechápou, co říkám.
But one thing is there, if there are some oppositions within, they will show –
Je tu však jedna věc, je-li v nich nějaká opozice, odpor, ukáže se to.
show very well – because they are so innocent and so simple,
Ukáže se to velmi snadno, protože ony jsou tak nevinné a prosté,
their innocence will help them to expose them to reality.
jejich nevinnost jim pomůže odhalit to realitě.
I hope you all look after your children, guide them properly
Doufám, že se o svoje děti všichni staráte, řádně je vedete
and take them to a level of understanding that they understand what is their position,
a dostáváte je na úroveň, na níž pochopí, jaké je jejich místo,
what qualities they should have, why will they be respected.
jaké mají mít kvality, díky čemu budou respektovány.
You’ll be amazed, that their behaviour will change
Budete udiveni, jak jejich chování změní
the behaviour of all the other children.
chování všech ostatních dětí.
What I have to say that nobody should think that you are very grown-up
Musím říci, že nikdo by si neměl myslet, že jste velmi dospělí
because you can keep quiet, sit quietly and all that, no.
kvůli tomu, že umíte být tiše, sedět klidně a tak dále. Ne.
You are grown-up only if you can imbibe the qualities of Shri Ganesha.
Jste dospělí, pouze pokud dokážete absorbovat kvality Šrí Ganéši.
I have seen people who are very grown-up still do not have simple qualities
Viděla jsem velmi vyzrálé lidi, kteří přesto nemají prosté kvality
of chastity, of honesty.
cudnosti, upřímnosti.
They don’t have, and they can’t have, because they don’t think it is important.
Nemají je a nemohou je mít, protože je nepovažují za důležité.
So, I leave it to you to find out Shri Ganesha within yourself.
Takže to nechám na vás, abyste v sobě našli Šrí Ganéšu.
I enjoy their company because they are so innocent
Já si jejich společnost užívám, protože jsou tak nevinné
and so simple-hearted and I like them very, very much.
a mají tak prosté srdce a já je mám velice ráda.
So, you should not get afraid or frightened of their mischief.
Takže, neměli byste mít obavy nebo strach z jejich rošťáctví.
On the contrary, you should know they deserve much more love,
Naopak byste měli vědět, že ony si zaslouží mnohem více lásky,
much more understanding and much more scope to grow.
mnohem více porozumění a mnohem více prostoru, aby vyrostly.
I hope by the time they will be of your age, they’ll be great Sahaja Yogis.
Doufám, že než dosáhnou vašeho věku, budou skvělí sahadžajogíni.
They’ll understand what we are doing here.
Budou chápat, co tady děláme.
I had to face mountains of nonsense with the older people,
Musela jsem se potýkat s hromadou nesmyslů ze strany dospělých,
but these won’t have that. They’ll be very simple, very sweet
ale tyto děti takové nebudou. Budou velmi prosté, velmi sladké
and they’ll understand love.
a budou rozumět lásce.
So I would say we can allow these children to go out and play
Řekla bych tedy, že bychom těmto dětem měli dovolit jít si hrát ven
and somebody can look after them, so that you’ll be at peace.
a někdo se o ně může starat, abyste vy byli v klidu.
Who can take them out?
Kdo je může vzít ven?
You can give Me flowers. If you have got flowers, I’ll take them.
Můžete mi dávat květiny. Pokud máte květiny, vezmu si je.
Thank you.
Děkuji.
Thank you very much.
Děkuji mnohokrát.
What is it? Boy: Chocolate. Pujari: Chocolate.
Co je to? Čokoláda. Čokoláda.
Boy: Yes, chocolate. Pujari: Chocolate. Chocolate, Shri Mataji.
Ano, čokoláda. Čokoláda. Čokoláda, Šrí Mátadží.
Thank you. Thank you very much.
Děkuji. Děkuji mnohokrát.
Thank you.
Děkuji.
Avinash: Can we have some volunteers? Please, take the children out.
Jsou zde nějací dobrovolníci? Prosím, vezměte děti ven.
Shri Mataji would like the children to play outside.
Šrí Mátadží by ráda, aby si děti hrály venku.
Can we have some mothers, some aunties if they can please take them out?
Můžeme poprosit nějaké matky, nějaké tety, aby je vzaly ven?
So we can proceed, please.
Abychom mohli pokračovat. Prosím!
Any volunteers, anyone?
Nějací dobrovolníci, kdokoli?
If Yuva Shakti...
Juva šakti...